[Music]
so yeah I mean the so this talk is gonna
be primarily a kind of like theoretical
you know in silico active inference kind
of talk I'll try to sprinkle in some
empirical data here in there but but so
yeah my um so you know one of my major
interests is in more or less ways of
understanding conscious and unconscious
emotional processes in the context of
emotional disorders and specifically
I've been really interested in seeing if
you can find ways to you know understand
these sorts of processes add a
computational level of description and
so I'll tell you about one particular
type of emotion cognition interaction
that I've done a fair amount of work on
and recently have tried to develop deep
act of inference models of so and the
main the main kind of goal with this and
this the specific type of emotion
puckish interaction that'll tell you
about is really to an individual
difference variable called trade
emotional awareness and and the idea is
to use it as just an example of sort of
a relevant trade trade psychological
difference that's sort of clinically
relevant where the idea is is that
hopefully even though you have this sort
of single phenotype of low emotional
awareness that's just something
clinically relevant and that doesn't
mean that there's a one-to-one mapping
between that phenotype and the
underlying mechanisms that are causing
it and so the hope is to use both neural
imaging measures and computational
modeling to sort of figure out okay what
are all the different possible
mechanisms that could be causing this
can we use that to figure out ways to
identify which mechanisms are operating
in which people and then use that to
inform treatment selection on an
individual basis and potentially the
treatment development so that's that's
the kind of general aim I have with
using emotional
as an example so first I'll kind of give
you some background context what is
trade emotional awareness and a little
bit about its clinical relevance and
I'll then give you a crash course on
what we've called the three process
model of emotional episodes this is a
very kind of kind of like broad way of
dividing up different processes they
contribute to what happens when you have
an emotional experience and that we have
more or less come up with as a way to
kind of tease apart what the different
places are in that process of having an
emotional experience where things can
kind of be different between different
people and that could explain
differences in what happens in your body
what happens when you feel what happened
in your body how you interpret it how
you use it to make decisions things like
that and then I'll tell you about the
kind of active inference version of this
that I put together at UCL and then
science and what if anything that might
have to add in terms of understanding
possible mechanisms okay so first thing
emotional awareness and it is it so some
people it's just kind of this common
clinical observation that some people
understand their emotions or have
trouble they some people a lot more
trouble recognizing and understanding
their emotions than other people do and
at at a low level this can lead to
things like mistaking negative emotions
for signs of sickness clues the kind of
thing like somatization or somatoform
disorders and some people kind of divide
up emotion space in a really coarse
brain way like they just kind of feel
bad or good but yeah that's about it
which is it all that action getting
right if I know I'm sad I have a much
better sense of what the possible causes
of what the likely causes are what I got
to do to regulate my emotions etc so bad
versus good isn't all that informative
or action guiding and it also for the
same reason can lead to poor
interpersonal problem-solving
you know if I'm not good at recognizing
my own emotions cry also am I good at
understanding other people's right and
so there's a lot of ways that this kind
of plausibly has an influence and
socially and in terms of
regulation for yourself and so
unsurprisingly almost also I think
psychotherapeutic approaches aim to
improve emotional awareness in one way
or another so the main sort of
instruments that we've used to measure
emotional awareness is something called
the levels of emotional are in a scale
and it's technically performance based
so it's based on self-report but it's
performance based in the sense that it's
not based on what you believe in
yourself report and basically what it
does is it just asks you to describe how
you'd feel in like 20 different
hypothetical situations and then it just
takes the sorts of terms you use and
then just scores them based on their
kind of level of specificity more or
less so like if you say you're sick
that'd be like one point it's like a
ploy somatic kind of thing if you just
say bad or good there'd be two points
use a single emotion word like sadness
or anger the three points if you can
talk about say feeling multiple things
at once before so that's the main way
that people sort of objectively or
performance based kind of get a sense of
what cognitive the wet way what sort of
concepts you actually use to understand
your experience spontaneously when
you're thinking about it and and there's
a pretty sort of large literature on
this nowadays so lower le a s4's have
been found in quite a large number of
different emotional disorders as well as
I'm just as democratical disorders and
even things like is such a hypertension
and or irritable bowel syndrome and
higher scores are associated with
greater empathy emotion recognition
openness to experience lower impulsivity
it's a lots of things like this and it's
because of that reason in part it is
part of the RDoc matrix so largely by
just with motivating its importance and
so then i mean the idea is like i
mentioned before and it would be helpful
if you want to know what the cause of
this is in different people to have some
understanding of what the underlying
cognitive a neural processes are and
really the only way so our attempt to
try to do that was to use this kind of
broad three process model the thing that
will tell you about and so I can't
really go through all
the kind of supportive evidence to back
everything I'm gonna say up so but we've
published a number of a series of
reviews kind of covering this and
updating it in various ways but I'm sad
I was going to show you a fun video
imagine that you were watching a car
really serenely going down the road and
then like a zombie jumping up at the
screen and screaming at you you should
have all jumped at which point I would
have said okay what just happened right
and I would have used that to guide you
through the process model of an emotion
episode so you missed out but so this is
in the kind of box ology depiction with
the three process model is the more or
less you start out with some sort of
event it could be real it could be
remembered it can be imagined but you're
representing some event right in some
way and then once it's represented then
you both implicitly and explicitly
evaluate along a bunch of different
dimensions this can be really a little
level like condition response kind of
thing but it also could be higher level
like you know is this something
controllable is this congruent with my
goals and you know things like things
like that and so that is what we call
the initiator effective response
generation processes the idea here is
based on that evaluation you have some
kind of allostatic prediction right
about what sorts of cognitive and
metabolic resources you're gonna have to
bring to the table in order to deal with
it and bring yourself sort of back to
preferred States and that responds
broadly again has two different kind of
components to it has a cognitive
component or a central component and
then AM peripheral physiological
component so the end the cognitive
component is going to be things like
initiating attention
those interpretation biases motivations
to say approachable anything with that
whereas the involuntary bodily response
the peripheral component it's going to
be things like automatic changes in
facial expression automatic changes in
heart rate muscle tension things like
that and so once that all kind of gets
going and I should say this is all kind
of going at every moment so it's all
feeding back influence again as well but
then you kind of have some update in
your model what it does it just happen
right what what what just changed in my
body and how do I interpret it so and
I'll go into more detail on that but
this is me where you'd say okay I feel
an increase in heart rate I interpret
that as indicating that I'm afraid right
something like that and then finally
it's important to realize that at least
briefly there's evidence to suggest that
all of these things can be briefly
represented unconsciously without you
being aware of it so there is this sort
of further process that you need where
these representations are say are
selected and sort of maintained active
in some way so you can kind of hold in
working memory and use them to make the
deliberative decision we've just called
that conscious access working memory you
know access to working memory something
like that and so yeah as a fear example
had you seen the jump-scare you know it
would have been like event screams
zombie you know the evaluation
unexpected potential danger you know
some low-level association between loud
scream and danger and then you would
have had some change in your body that
you could sort of represent that way
this is actually data based on you have
a bunch of people kind of draw they feel
on their body when they say they're
feeling different emotions and they
there are these kind of like interesting
reliable perceived patterns and so you
have something like that
I'm gonna have the initiation of some
kind of threat bias and some avoidance
motivation you know you'd feedback and
you'd represent those bodily sensations
you'd identify as corresponding to your
learned concept of fear and then if that
all gets accessible you'd be able to say
I just got scared because of the abrupt
unexpected job together right so that's
kind of so process one generate the
effect of respond
process to represent it and this kind of
hierarchical way and process three gain
access to it hold in working memory to
use it and I can I can do this for other
things right so it could be you got
denied a promotion that was goal
incongruent and you direct the blame at
other people say your boss great you
have this anger kind of like bodily
feeling right it's really active
negativity bias but an approach
motivation right you represent the and
that you think you're angry and then
that becomes accessible and you could
say I'm really angry at my boss because
he didn't give me the promotion and I
deserved it right so hopefully that
gives you guys kind of the intuition and
if you kind of zoom in on this internal
state representation part that's gonna
be a big chunk of the modeling then you
can kind of think about it is again that
kind of low-level you you have this
feedback from your body and you
representing something like a valence
valence interoceptive representation
along with some semadar motor stuff like
facial expression changes things like
that but then you can have to map that
in some way up to some higher-level
interpretation and that's going to
depend on what you've learned
right like emotion concepts for example
are different in different cultures so
it's not like there's one kind of true
answer about what of the bajillion
different multidimensional by states it
could be in and some particular emotion
concept but you make sense of it in some
way you know that you've learned and
there can be differences in the
granularity your specificity here action
guiding this right over the ways you
come to carve it off and so this could
again be you feel a body feeling like
that you map it on to sadness with
priors that come from the cognitive part
like unexpectedness loss uncontrollable
and this is actually meant to be like
fully sort of general and analogous to
say like a visual case forgets to say a
visual image like that you'd map it on
to the concepts trouble right in the
context of other aspects that you're
representing say like tools shed and i
should say that this is like a huge
simplification right there's definitely
not two levels of representation in body
states if you're interested in this
we've published a paper a couple of
years ago
laying out based on a lot of kind of
just nitty-gritty about anatomical and
physiological responses Integra
characterizations that you can kind of
lay out and even this is oversimplified
8-level kind of hierarchy for how you
represent interceptive States and kind
of integrate them with higher-level
information from other senses in memory
and but good enough for our purposes
here and and then the final process and
so we've kind of based this largely on
this work on what are called global
workspace models of consciousness or at
least the empirical support for them
which broadly shows again that say if
you play somebody a sound but you they
don't hear it because it's distracted by
something you get this kind of local
representation in auditory cortex but
only when it's detected does it have
this kind of global broad influence on
Association cortices throughout the
brain see ideas consciousness requires
accessibility of the information carried
by that local representation via this
broad sort of influence updating a model
more broadly you can think about it that
way and so here the idea would be
something like you can represent you
could have some representation of a body
state like that you could have primed a
concept like sadness and you could have
primed you know things like
unexpectedness loss etc but that may or
may not you know become broadly
accessible and if it is then you could
say things like I'm sad because I just
lost a friend and I don't have much
energy right now but maybe only the body
state becomes accessible then you be
able to say I feel really a little
energy but I don't know why you know
maybe I'm sick or you could have access
even to the interpretation but not to
the underlying sort of causes right and
then you could say and this happens
fairly often right I feel where it's out
of I'm not sure why there's in real life
there's a kind of top-down process in
the sense that you're in a context and
there are norms and expectations in what
you might feel in that
so those schemas are sort of available
as a level priors yeah and you could you
can think about that as as priors coming
in part from this kind of cognitive
appraisal dimension sorts of things but
that could also act as priors on just
what emotion concept you you think best
fits the I guess I'm thinking of it even
as prior to having any bodily feeling
and as to priming that in some ways and
maybe even increasing the likelihood of
having certain or even selecting out of
sort of white noise bodily feelings the
possibly of labeling something that
doesn't have a strong valence attached
to it but assimilating it into that
expectation yeah no I totally agree I
mean there's questions about whether
that's coming in at the response
generation part or after great I mean
either you're not generating that
response to begin with in which case
you're not gonna have a bodily feeling
because the body doesn't do anything
right or it could be the way interpreted
after the fact right so I mean it seems
like this is where you can kind of
disentangle a couple different things
potentially so I don't think I probably
understand nothing I mean nothing I've
been talking about I think is that the
level low enough to be something like
painting
yeah I mean there is I mean there is
there's a lot of work on pain or
presentation actually within that like
kobol workspace you know sort of
approach to conscious processing and
there I mean depending on the reason or
the actual basically their circumstances
in which the pain representation
probably gets a lot higher up like into
the insula for example but you still
don't become it doesn't have to be but
it wouldn't have to be conscious that
could that representation can happen
unconscious I mean we but so anyway so I
mean that's that's kind of just a brief
kind of crash course and just just to
kind of frame a few of the kind of
neuroimaging results that all kind of
you know sprinkle in throughout the way
and I am we have kind of proposed and
based in part on some of our research a
kind of tentative um kind of large-scale
model for the way to think about these
processes in the brain and based mainly
on work on the function of large-scale
brain networks the idea this is that I
mean you know there's still kind of up
in the air exactly the right way to
interpret these things but while you
can't really say conditional on knowing
that a particular brain area activated
you can't really know that much about
psychological what psychological
function was going
looks like you can actually do this
quite a bit better if you know what
brain areas you're talking to one
another
there's no connectivity and so based on
that kind of thing you know people have
kind of looked at a number of studies
and proposed and for instance this paper
by Lisa Feldman baronage a StopIt a ways
of understanding kind of broad domain
general functions of these different
networks and you know one for example
this thing though in cream here the
limbic network looks like it's pretty
strongly involved in representing and
regulating this promoter states and so
it's kind of a prime target for
generating these sorts of effective
bodily responses and response to
evaluations whereas the somatic motor
Network here and salient salience
network components especially sort of
insula and anterior cingulate and look
like some of that is also involved in
the generation process but also looks
like it's pretty important for
representing interoceptive and
somatosensory states to be a lot of the
kind of body state representation stuff
and the default mode network thus can
come here is pretty strongly implicated
in a lot of conceptualization related
processes right so multimodal
integration trying to make sense of
things as a semantic level I'm watching
these sort of large scale simulations
we're kind of like don't along temporal
scales based on and drawing from one for
memory things like that and then the
yellow thing executive control Network
largely implicating things like working
memory control and it's a big chunk of
what activates during conscious versus
unconscious contrast and so the kind of
thing we have in mind is you know you
have some perceptual representation it
either gets interpreted you know via
default Network processes or directly
has some sort of conditioned Association
thing with limbic Network processes that
ends up generating a change in body
state and some modular Tori effects on
cognition likely based on influencing
these sort of broaden rule module Ettore
patterns from brain stem or modulators
that be kind of the you know tweaking
precision here and there kind of a thing
and body state information then feeds
back in and updates your model and so
representing your body in a different
state now
that then can feed back and further get
interpreted and conceptualized as an
emotion or as something else and via the
same sort of default Network processes
all that stuff can then compete for
maintenance and working memory and then
all of it can both consciously and
unconsciously then influence actions
life in some way right so again very
very broad we do have some studies
consistent with it but I wouldn't say
it's you know at all kind of you know
take you to the bank just kind of
something guide hypotheses and so you
know we've thought ok well you could
have individual differences in the
response generation stuff in the
representation stuff or an accessibility
and those could each you could tweak
each of those independently and produce
a similar kind of phenotype right so
different things could be going on in
different people and knowing what's
going on and what person would be
important potentially in terms of their
veteran sorry would you classify facial
expression and display as part of a
response because because there are big
cultural differences and sort of
training for the ability to issue
display yeah absolutely and there can be
some kind of you know top-down control
stuff to beret where you could have the
automatic tendency to do one thing but
then suppress it give them some norm
right and so that also it gets pretty
complicated best yes
here on the course very general level
without even getting into cultural
differences to get a sense of the
general picture it seems to me maybe we
need to talk about community meaning is
obvious culturally framed so
experiencing a deep emotion for humans
has something to do with the attribution
of meaning funding like a narrative the
cost related cause and then say the
struming to receptive surprise it
probably table go back you know yeah
absolutely
no I don't disagree at all I mean I and
I mean not you know I'd like to pack
some of that into you know the sort of
you know like the hierarchically
expanded version of this like a value of
appraisal sort of thing I'm talking
about right where you can definitely
have one of these top-down influences
even when they're not culturally
specific right like amygdala they make a
little respond pretty strongly to images
of food when someone's hungry but not
when they're full for example right so
I'm going to sort of top-down an
expectation about what's relevant you
know in your situation be very context
specific right so I mean there's
definitely a lot of that and a lot of
the way that you evaluate things in
terms of say consistency with norms and
values and consistency with your current
goals all of that is going to have very
much a sort of top-down component and
influence the response you have to
whatever you think is going on but it
will also influence other things to you
right like the way you interpret what
state you're in half of the facts yeah I
just totally agree okay so like I
mentioned we've done sort of a number of
studies over the last few years testing
various aspects of this and finding
neuroimaging results both structural and
functional in we at least think are
consistent with it like I said I
mentioned some of them along the way but
and all of this is primarily to motivate
why it's worth trying to do a fancy
active inference model version so since
we haven't really talked about active
inference at all at least not the Markov
decision process for me
and I could probably be worth giving
people kind of a quick walk through and
you know if you've seen this kind of
Bayes net depiction before can be kind
of intimidating it's a billion variables
you know doesn't say it doesn't say
anywhere what they mean and so I'll try
to give you kind of a kind of step by
step here real briefly if you get rid of
most of that and you just have this oath
thing at the bottom this connection up
that we'll call a and then this s thing
which is the state view the state you
believe you're in and then D which is
essentially your prior expectations
about states then this is just a pretty
simple sort of depiction of kind of
one-step Bayesian inference you have
some prior expectation you get some
observation you infer what that
observation means based in part on what
you expected ahead of time right and the
Saudi is your priors the a matrix
essentially just describes your beliefs
about the relationships between States
and observations right like something
white and circular is more consistent
with baseball than football right I mean
that's basically all it all it amounts
to right so then if you're going to to
expand on that then you know we don't
just observe things statically right so
you need a temporal component to this
and that's where this B matrix thing
comes in so that's essentially your
beliefs about how things how states
evolve over time so once you figure out
what you believe about what you're in
about where you were what state you were
in at time 1 this B matrix lets you
gives you a prior and ok what a state do
I expect nowt to be in at time 2 and so
then that becomes your prior you get an
observation at the next time point and
then you infer a posterior over States
at time 2 which can then also feedback
and update your beliefs about what
happened at time 1 but but no central
all you're doing is just making this
thing temporarily extend it so beliefs
at one time quite act as priors for the
next time plane but this is still fully
perceptual and so then to add an action
model on top of it and you have to add
these things so PI here is just your set
of allowable policies
choices you take yourself to have and
this G thing is the expected free energy
of each policy essentially Co encodes
your something like the estimated value
you assigned each policy and and that is
evaluated with respect to this c-vector
thing which encodes more or less what
you want and what you don't want so an
active inactive inference Linga what's
your prior preference distribution and
and then finally so okay just give you a
sense so GE the expected free energy
that is one way of displaying the
equation I won't go into it in detail
but the thing to understand more or less
is it has a component that involves
minimizing the deviation between the
outcomes that you think are going to
happen if you choose a certain policy
and the and your preferred outcomes see
secondly you're minimizing the public
label divergence between the outcomes
you think are gonna happen and the
outcomes you want give me a choice you
could make and then the second component
and involves a way of also basically
policies that are having higher value if
you think that them leading you to
transition to certain states it's going
to be really informative it's going to
minimize some certainty more about what
states are actually
so yeah so I mean all you should take
this to mean is just that the the value
of policies so that the posterior
distribution over PI is going to be
based on the free energy calculated with
respect the expected free energy
calculate the perspex you see so so more
or less just this just means policies
have higher values if they're gonna get
you closest to what you want and if
they're also going to give you more
information about where you know what's
actually the case because a lot of times
before you can know what you should do
to get what you want you have to know
enough about you know what the state of
affairs actually is and so then finally
the last step and is adding these
additional things and which won't matter
a ton for what I'll show you but more or
less these additional kind of hyper
parameters allow you to allow the model
to maintain estimates it's essentially
its own confidence in its actor model
itself so this sort of beta-gamma thing
is more or less a way of having a prior
and then updating this expected
precision term which more or less
reflects your confidence in how good
your action model is and that ends up
actually trading off influence with this
ething which is essentially a fixed form
prior over policies so it's sort of the
policies you expect a priori to select
over others take thing we're it's not
like that just like habits more or less
and so the way this ends up working is
is that policy selection will be more
driven by habits if gamma is low if you
have very little evidence there but very
little confidence in your action
and having a prior prior for high beta
is going to buy us your initial gamma so
it toward being lower which means you're
going to favor acting based on habits so
that's the way of interpreting this
thing and and so that that will happen
kind of just on its own I mean that bull
just falls out of the expected for
energy equation right so so you just
have the epistemic component is that
latter component and the pragmatic
component is the the earlier part of the
right side so so for instance like it
just it just will happen automatically
that whatever value whatever whichever
policy has the lowest expected free
energy will will be a trade-off between
those two there's nothing waiting than
outside of just so an empirical sound
like them so if you want to like fit
behavior empirically you know I try to
do this before where you can actually
throw in an additional throw in an
additional term it was actually wait you
have a stem a component versus the
pragmatic component but in practice what
will happen is because the because the M
the C vector because the the magnitudes
preferences can vary continuously then
just the higher the magnitude is the the
greater the weight the pragmatic
component will have so having a low
magnitude C just automatically makes it
so you're more driven by this nice value
like you have production to see so maybe
if you're hungry then you start being
temporary yeah it's gonna say yeah
that's that's not built into the
standard NDP formulation but yes I mean
there's there's definitely fancier
things you could do Casper has tried to
do some of them well stay tuned about so
so anyway and just briefly I mean you
can't really see this a lot well but and
the active inference formulation I'm
just showing you also has this kind of
proposed accompanying neural process
theory it allows you to essentially
simulate um plausible neural activation
the you want to see given the dynamics
in the model it's not gonna be that
important for what I'll show you but
more or less and you just end up and you
end up being able to derive these update
equations that just cast the essentially
the equations for updating free energy
and for excitement free energy in terms
of these two different sorts of
prediction errors called state
prediction errors and outcome prediction
errors and then those then those errors
then feed into calculating or updating
the free energy and expected for energy
estimates and then you can just do used
agreed units that creative dissent on
those and what ends up happening is that
belief updates for a moment moment
correspond to changes in them activation
levels and different of these kind of
simulated neurons whereas the actual
matrix entries like they the major can
matrix entries in a and B and C in D
that indicate more your kind of like
more stable beliefs about relationships
between things those end up
corresponding to synaptic connection
strengths which you can learn but you
update them more slowly across trials
but like I said it won't matter that
much
so applying that them to understand
emotional awareness and is something
that we've done for you and and one
thing so you can just ignore this top
part basically all of it all that adding
the second level on means is that you
just attack the same thing on a top what
I just showed you so so the state your
state inference at the end of each trial
at the lower level just ends up being
the observation that feeds into the same
exact structure at the level above so
for instance you'd run the lower level
like three times and then that would
correspond to three observations over
time by the higher level and so for the
kind of task we put together to model
emotional awareness is this kind of
emotion focus working memory task more
or less the idea is is that the agent is
presented with some kind of effective
response at time one and has to infer
what emotion it's feeling and then some
time goes by its presented with another
affective response has to infer what
it's feeling now and then this kind of
delay period where it's gonna hold on to
that information and maybe later at
which at which point it's exposed to a
third an affective response then it has
to say okay is what I'm feeling now the
same or different from some of the stuff
I was doing before so it's kind of a
reflection on current versus past
emotional experience this is actually
you know thing not too dissimilar from
stuff that can happen in therapy right
and it's also well yeah I'll get to this
so but the so the idea ultimately with
with the model as I'll show you is you
end up having these two nested tasks so
first you have this effective response
that kind of comes up from your body and
you represent it and which can have you
know various dimensional components
valence arousal motivation your kind of
interpretation of a situation things
like that and the first task is to infer
which emotion concept that you currently
have acquired best accounts for that
pattern lower level representations but
at a second level you have to take that
and map it into working memory then you
have to kind of do something with it
memory to be able to self-report it and
use it in collaborative cognition so
task one is just to figure out what
you're feeling at a given moment and
task two is kind of accumulated evidence
for what different things you're feeling
over time and then use them to
deliberate to make a choice and I just
say this particular task is motivated by
the fact we've actually done some
empirical work on emotion focused
working memory and with just little
tasks like this where you show people
emotional images and you either ask them
to hold what emotion they felt in mind
or just hold the visual image in mind or
hold like their bodily sensations in
mind or hold nothing in mind over some
delay period then they have to make some
you know judgment afterwards about
whatever they were holding in mind and
what you can find is actually consistent
with the three process model I showed
you you get in the emotion condition
relative to just holding visual images
in mind you get a lot of this medial
prefrontal and anterior insula kind of
default mode Network kind of stuff
whereas in in both conditions actually
emotion greater than rest and also
envision greater than rest you get this
dorsal lateral front a parietal thing do
you expect for any kind of working
memory so so it's kind of like the
representation may be specific but
what's holding it in mind is general and
it's also falls on previous we're
showing that just when people pay
attention to their emotions and just
recognize them you also get this but so
okay so so the first level in the model
formally so it has this kind of
structure where there are a bunch of
different things that you can observe
you can observe different balances
different arousal levels different
approach or avoidance motivations and
three dozen general different kind of
evaluated contexts that you could be in
its got like a neutral context to social
threat context or a physical threat
context and again this is very just kind
of toy model to get across the general
structure and but the idea is is that
what it is to have a quiet different
emotion
concepts and is to have learnt
particular mappings to different sorts
of regularities that occur across those
different lower-level representations so
for instance and you can encode you
encode that in for instance the a matrix
here
so this basically says that sadness
corresponds to negative valence low
arousal avoidance and social correct
right whereas happy on the end
corresponds to neutral wait I might I
might have that wrong
oh no sorry that's heart attack like
that so it's sad this panic statement
heart attack so happy is negative high
arousal avoid and physical right so I
mean that's that's kind of what it looks
like this is encoded in those
connections more or less and for this
particular model we're just assuming
that within a trial and I motion remain
stable and so the B matrix is an
identity matrix and and then down here
but process right you'd interpret your
situation a certain way it's selective
stay to like increase heart rate policy
right or something something more high
dimensional than that obviously but and
so we're not explicitly modeling that
there we're just assuming a particular
response has been generated that it's
consistent with your evaluation of the
context and that you're just being the
agents kind of being presented with the
result of that response and so whichever
is highlighting here is that we're kind
of assuming that's the case but we're
not actually modeling the response
generation that that even lower level
policy selection first and and then the
second component of the first level is
there is a kind of selective attention
component building and the idea here is
to figure out what you're feeling
you have to kind of selectively attend
say okay what they'll into my feeling
okay you know what does my body say feel
like oh or I feel like do I feel like I
should run away or you know approach you
know what do i what are my actual
beliefs about situation things like that
this is actually the exact sort of thing
that often people do in like cognitive
therapy for example where you can
attract patterns right and like what
you're thinking what you're feeling what
you did you know stuff like that to try
to increase people's awareness so it's
meant to kind of mimic that process and
so the idea is is that the agent has to
kind of choose what to pay attention to
across the trial to infer what emotion
makes the most yeah best fits the
experience and so you can kind of the
way that gets implemented is that the
actual the actual probability
distribution in the a matrix is becomes
higher dimensional essentially it's
different conditional attentional that
you're in so if you're in the attentive
valence state then the a matrix looks
like that if it's a tend to arousal
looks like that but to tend to
motivation it looks like that and if
it's attend to context it looks like
that right so that's that's the way it
ends up being structured and so so for
the first level then you can use that
all by itself without tacking on the
second level at all to do this kind of
single single emotion recognition
process right the emotional state
representation component of the three
process model and and this is what it
looks like when the model performs
successfully so here the agent was
presented with an effective response
that was most consistent with sadness
according to the concept it had learned
and so you can see what happened as it
first chooses to pay attention to
context and then it chooses to pay
attention to arousal and then at that
point it says okay I'm confident based
on the social threat context and low
arousal that sadness is the right
so report status and then you can just
kind of see over here how the confidence
kind of shifts slowly toward being
confident most confident in sadness by
the third time going to trial there on
the right and this stuff on the bottom
is just kind of simulated and simulated
like regulated potentials that you would
see but don't worry about that so then
the the second level then and the
working memory component involves doing
a sort of similar thing so basically
what you have here is is now once the
agents inferred what emotion they sad or
panic or what other bodily states sick
or heart attack you know however it's
categorizing its data at a given time
those provide evidence over time for
different things that could be held in
working memory so this could be just
being sad just feeling panic feeling
both sadness and panic etc etc for
different combinations and then you have
another independent hidden state factor
that corresponds to the comparison state
so essentially what you find out at the
end
the third emotion that you're feeling
you have to judge whether it's the same
or different than one of the original
two and so the a matrix for that one
just looks like that and which I can go
into if you want but it just describes
that mapping I just described and then
there are a couple additional hidden
state factor you have to build in here
like you have to build in beliefs about
the task structure the agent has to know
for instance that it's at time point one
you know in the working memory task time
point to whether it's in the delay
period etc and then it also has to
choose to report at the end of the trial
just two things just same or different
you know feeling the same as before
we're not and that leads to observations
where it gets some feedback were either
it was you know it gets it right or it
gets it wrong and the C matrix here just
basically says it wants to get it right
it does want to get it wrong so this
part would be modeling the kind of
conscious access process more where once
you have these representation
it's you map them in and hold them in
mind you can do something with them and
so a successful trial with the model
here looks like this so at so the first
time point so the this middle panel here
corresponds to the single state
inference at the lower level so first it
infers nothing so we just call that
blank the second time Boyd and at first
it was feeling sadness that the third
time panic then blank again because it's
the delay period then at the fourth time
point it thinks it felt neutral and then
blank again that's just the structure of
trial and what what it experienced at
each moment and you can see at the
second level what happens is it slowly
builds a confidence over time that the
sadness plus panic state is the right
one right and then it holds that
information in mind over this delay
period after it observes a second
emotion and then uses that at the end to
choose to say different way in which
case it observes that it was correct
what do you say and so I mean it is
these are beliefs about how how it feels
changed over time right well I'm except
for instance say say you had a panic I
mean this is uncommon you have a panic
attack and then you're really sad the
rostral day that you had a panic attack
so so that the the potential usefulness
of this kind of thing other than just
showing you know fancy seeming flashy
simulations is that you know it allows
you to kind of interrogate what are the
different ways that things can go wrong
what are the different possible
mechanisms by which things could break
down okay and where you could have
different potential intervention targets
so the first one and all this sort of
mentioned this really briefly is just
you can maybe you're just failing to
generate responses at all in which case
just means visceral policies aren't
being selected in the first place
there's nothing to explicitly simulate
there but I mention it because it's
probably not unreasonable thing
thing happens in some cases so for
instance in one study we did we actually
did find that the thinner viscera motor
cortices were the lower emotional
awareness towards work so suggestive
more interestingly we've done some we
reported in these case studies these
extreme sort of rare cases where and for
instance this woman just reports she's
never experienced an emotion her whole
life just flat just emotional this
experience and she's really like
paradoxically distressed by head because
she ultimately committed suicide because
she said her life felt meaningless
without any emotion and when we did like
when we did like skin conductance
responses on her totally flat no
responses to emotional images whatsoever
but but it was more just like they were
kind of incoherent responses because she
would be talking in a therapy session
about like for instance her marriage
feeling and tears of like well up in her
eyes but her face would be totally flat
otherwise and like therapist would say
hey it looks like you're like crying she
like she like yeah you know I don't
control it as my eyes just do that
sometimes like and so point being it's
not inconsistent that this is the
explanation in some cases and I mean
there is some actual developmental
literature you know suggesting ways this
could kind of happen too right so if you
look at and the sort of drawing version
of how people's body feels when they're
feeling different emotions
six-year-old it's like if you look at
sadness six-year-olds it's pretty like
nondescript it's basically nothing
whereas in adults it's really highly
specific right so you could imagine ways
in which the six year old version just
persists under certain sorts of like
unfortunate developmental so the next
version so just like all failure to
infer and this is this corresponds to
something we've talked about in the past
called affective Ignatia the idea being
something a lot like a visual agnosia
where yeah okay right so the basic idea
is kind of just like with a lake and
associative visual agnosia
where you could have like a an
experience
sexual experience like that trouble
right person could drop for you and
everything but you ask them what is it
they have no idea right or they miss
recognize it as something else
sorry ghee there's a similar sort of
thing that could happen but in these
sort of emotional realm effect of ik
know Jia where a person perceives and
could describe the bodily feeling but
just doesn't recognize what it means and
and often what will happen in this case
is that it'll be miss recognized with
something else
and so in this matters ation case you
might say think you're feeling you know
have a bodily sensation consistent with
fear or panic but instead infer of this
as a heart attack which often happens
people with panic attacks often run to
the ER right and so so one way to make
sense of this or potentially right would
be if a person's just learned to have a
really strong prior expectation for
threatening somatic states and one
interesting example of this is people
with high anxiety sensitivity scores
like actually characterizes just that
and and this is actually something in
part that we talked about in a recent
paper we're trying to kind of give
explanations for why early adversity
it's actually associated with high
levels of chronic oh I don't have time
to get into it but if you're interested
and so here I mean it's interesting what
actually happens if you give the thing
higher prior expectations for sickness
and heart attack right for this
threatening somatic states then what
happens is basically the model this
jumps to conclusions too quickly like
all it does is pay attention to its
arousal level sees high arousal and
sight already know you know so it just
says it having a heart attack it doesn't
it's too confident right so it doesn't
pay attention to the context or anything
else that would allow it to say okay now
I'm probably just having some anxiety
yes so I'm not going to finish it at all
if I don't take power through here but
but at the end and so again I should
probably skip some of the empirical work
here just given time but basically we
have shown that if you look at people
with different emotional awareness
levels the default mode network actually
only activates more than some
representation systems if you have high
emotional awareness so so it looks like
you don't really differentiate emotions
from bodily sensations at the low end
which is kind of consistent with this
idea and so a third one so could be that
you just you just haven't acquired
emotion concepts right so consider like
a person who grows up in like an
environment with a lot of like just
early parental neglect you don't have
the attunement you don't have the you
know social feedback signals to learn
about these things and so you just don't
acquire them um and this is probably
also something that contributes a lot to
if you want to understand things like
the relationship between social support
and disease we've talked about in the
sort of computational variant of the
trying to understand the biopsychosocial
model in medicine and we've talked about
it this a little bit there but and you
yeah like if you don't have the early
support that you're not gonna learn the
things your needle you're gonna need to
learn and that can lead to a bunch of
things that can promote systemic disease
later in life and but so here um really
all you have to do to mimic not having
acquired emotion concepts is just to get
rid or flatten out the you know
connections between the emotion concepts
and what they predict right if those
days don't predict anything specific
that's the same thing as saying you
don't have those concepts and so if you
do that then let's get that and then
what happens is unsurprisingly and the
thing never really becomes very
confident no matter what it experiences
at the end of the day it's like okay I
have to report something so it just
reports that it feels bad it's not
confident knows the feeling an emotion
but it's not confident enough to pick a
specific one and it doesn't want to be
wrong so just as bad and and
interestingly this version predicts
you'd have much longer reaction times
right so in the first version if
somebody has a low emotional awareness
score they have a really fast reaction
time because they dump the conclusions
really quickly right whereas this person
sits around forever and along I don't
know what's going on right so like you
could actually test just based on
reaction times which one of these sorts
of mechanisms with most possible any
give them individual
let's just say I think that's a very
important distinction and finding
because you could also make the argument
that a distinction any good and bad is
just a very crude and low-level
distinction that should be made very
quickly right reptiles could decide
isn't good or bad right but this is
saying no actually it's really you are
it could be at least in certain people
yeah be able to say you have fast
reaction times you have solar reaction
times therefore a treat you or even a
for you a treatment be and again you
know just briefly I mean we've done some
work like with resting state functional
connectivity and showing that you know
if you think about functional
connections as reflecting differentiated
say like synaptic you know connection
patterns of correspondent learning and
then what we found is in both the
default Network and in salience Network
body see representation
regions you have much lower so at least
something about the fidelity of that
kind of processing is isn't is not as
great this is just some of the data and
correlations but but I should just
mention we have another paper that's
under review right now where we actually
simulate the emotion concept learning
process itself with active inference and
that also is kind of a cool story about
when learning can go wrong and but not
going to talk about that here and so
then a fourth possible mechanism is just
having learned by its patterns of
attention this is another thing that
comes in a lot actually when thinking
about chronic pain in the context of
chronic negative affective states and
but and we've talked about before but
here I mean it's pretty simple you just
you just use the e matrix thing the
prior prior ever policies and you just
say this person has a really strong
habit of only paying attention to
context right for an external attention
bias or this person has a really strong
prior that they're going to attend only
to the internal stuff right and I mean
kind of you know as it's set up you have
to integrate context information with
the bodies didn't for me
to be good at inferring you know what
you're feeling or understanding it and
so if you simulate these different sorts
of attentional biases you get low
emotional awareness behavior but they
have different patterns you know in one
if it's an external bias but they're
kind of like averse to paying attention
though their body altogether right then
they just end up reporting you know
patterns good whereas if they ignore
context and this hyper focus on their
body then they just tend to kind of
report kind of like an emotion thing or
a body thing kind of half and half right
they're just kind of inconsistent and
the fifth one again I'm just kind of
rushing through these quickly because
we're short on time and something that's
interesting in the context of borderline
personality disorder is this idea about
beliefs and emotional instability or
high emotional volatility if you just
believe that you could be sad in one
moment happy in the next and right if
you don't think emotions absolute
minimal amount of stability then it
actually becomes really hard to learn
about them or infer them if you have to
selectively integrate information about
them over time right so in this case you
just flatten out the B matrix down here
to say look like emotions are allowed to
transition to other emotions or to
somatic states within trial and then
what you end up with something like this
where the things just not confident at
every moment it just rechecks the same
thing I looked at before because then
something could have changed and when
you end up with this thing's like it
starts out believing that it was feeling
panic but by the end it self reports
that is feeling a heart attack you know
it's like I mean it might have started
out as just panic but now you know now
it's a heart attack
so it's another thing kind of
interesting and and then that the last
two mechanisms are when you have to
invoke front of his higher level right
the working memory level and here coming
again just review papers on stuff if
you're interested in more detail but the
idea is how do you kind of model this
presence or absence of this strong
connection on causal influence that
actually updates the higher level and
this is also motivated by some work
we've done and some graphic theoretical
Alice's that we've done showing that
actually if you look at individual
difference
is an emotional awareness they actually
correlate with lower network density and
with longer average path lengths so so
those are just two measures of
essentially a long range information
integration so if you have higher
emotional awareness
you're better at propagating the signals
over long ranges right so kind of
consistent with this general idea this
is a positive thing
and here it's a similar kind of trick
you just take these connections from the
first level of the second level and any
of them that involve updating based on
emotional information at the first level
you flatten out which is essentially the
same thing as saying the first level
representations no longer have causal
influence on the higher level right and
if you do that then what's really cool
is you get something a lot like
unconscious emotion priming right so the
first level it is representing sadness
and then panic and then neutral right
that's there but just in kind of this
prime state that could have some kind of
semantic priming effects but it doesn't
update the higher level at all so the
thing can't hold the emotions in mind
work with them at all and it gets it
wrong when it needs to report something
or think about supposedly I think about
what it's feeling and then the final one
and one that's kind of interesting in
clinical context with some of the
clinical clinicians that I've worked
with in the past has to do with this
idea about sort of state differences in
reflective capacity the idea here is is
that again the image doesn't show up
that well but there's this really like
well-known result that cognitive
performance like the ability kind of
reflect on things dying in control
working memory and all that stuff tends
to be best at this kind of middle level
of arousal if you're like really highly
anxious then all of a sudden you can't
reflect on anything at all and and
decision-making becomes a lot more
impulsive and I reflective typically not
adaptive and one way to think about this
is that in high arousal states and the
predictability for the precision
assigned to the higher levels of
processing like that reflect these sort
of long time scale regularities those
just kind of get assigned to a procedure
because
in threatening context sort of
historically yeah now where you're
eating right it doesn't make sense to
assign high precision to those to the
high levels in those contexts and so you
can kind of think about this as in a
state dependent way decreasing the
transition precision at the higher level
which Thomas Parr and other people have
previously already shown this is a way
to mimic lower working memory capacity
as well it's essentially the same kind
of idea so what happens in this case is
and even say if at timepoint two it knew
that it was feeling it was feeling in
this case panic then that just kind of
decays away over time so it can't
actually even though it knew it at one
point in time it can't hold it in mind
and actually use it and and so that's
just yet another kind of mechanism and
again I wish you could see it better on
the image because it it really does kind
of just decay away until the probability
distribution becomes flat by the end but
but so anyway so that I mean the idea is
just basically you can use this and you
can show look there's at least these
seven different independent mechanisms
that could be messed up or working
sub-optimally that could lead to the
same or very similar clinical phenotype
but they have different underlying
causes and you would target them
differently and we've actually enter in
our paper we actually outlined and you
can't see it but for each of the
different mechanisms there are different
sort of clinical evaluations that are
currently used different relevant
measures that are currently used try to
you could use to evaluate them and
different intervention and they look
like they target some more than others
and they're also gaps right where you
can design things that would more
effectively target one versus the other
but a lot of it is kind of out there
somewhere it's just not framed in this
way or selected you know treemail are
selected based on this kind of thing
and so the basic idea is is they like I
said there's a bunch of these different
possible mechanisms you could actually
test them based either on different
predicted normal response patterns or
behavioral patterns like reaction time
differences and and you know if that
ends up working right you have to do a
criminal experimental work to actually
test that but in principle you can use
that to identify mechanisms that operate
in single individuals and then use that
for targeted intervention so I'm with
that tons of people to acknowledge but
top of the list would be Carl first and
Thomas par Richard Lane Maxwell Kasper
and all Badcock
[Applause]
[Music]